Guide to the William E. Guckert Papers 1930-1977 AIS.1995.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
William E. Guckert Papers
1930-1977
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Guckert, William E.
AIS.1995.05
8.75 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
This collection contains the papers of William E. Guckert for the years 1930-1977. William E. Guckert was a leader in the environmental conservation movement in Pennsylvania. He began his career as secretary of the Allegheny County Sportsmen's League, then became a lobbyist with the State Land Reclamation Board, and ended as Director of the State Board of Surface Mine Reclamation. Most of the records in this collection deal with Guckert's conservation efforts on strip-mines and mine reclamation during his career.
History
William E. Guckert, 1908-1986, an early environmental conservationist, established laws pertaining to strip mines and mine drainage in Pennsylvania. Guckert began his conservationist career as secretary of the Allegheny County Sportsmen's League(ACSL). The ACSL was active in protecting, preserving, and conserving the natural resources of Pennsylvania and the nation. As secretary, Guckert helped lead the organization by calling attention to pollution, notably strip mines. In 1963, Guckert was selected to serve on the State Land Reclamation Board(SLRB), which advocated action against areas affected by strip-mining. Guckert acted as a lobbyist for the SLRB until 1967 when he was appointed Director of the State Bureau of Surface Mine Reclamation(SBSMR) by Governor Raymond Shafer. As director, Guckert established many of Pennsylvania's current conservation laws and awareness programs. He served as director of the SBSMR for ten years until retirement in 1977. William E. Guckert died on October 15, 1986, in Grove City, Mercer County, Pa.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the papers of William E. Guckert for the years 1930-1977. The concentration of papers from 1930-1950 deal with Guckert as secretary of the Allegheny County Sportsmen's League(ACSL). These records consist of meeting minutes, financial reports, constitution by-laws, membership, and correspondence. Most of the records are in the form of correspondence since Guckert was secretary of the ACSL. Guckert's Papers cover the State Land Reclamation Board period of 1963-1967. These records document how the ACSL helped push conservation legislation through lobbyist groups such as; the Allegheny Solid Waste Advisory Committee, the PA Sanitary Water Board, and the State Land Reclamation Board. Most of the SLRB's efforts can be seen in the reports and subject files on conservation. Guckert was Director of the State Bureau of Surface Mine Reclamation(SBSMR) from 1967 to 1977. It is evident that Guckert transferred many of his SLRB files to the SBSMR when Director. These records include legislation on land conservation, clean streams, strip-mines, and acid mine drainage. The last group of records consist of Guckert's research, news article clippings, and various large maps, that span 1967 to 1977. The files are ordered alphabetically by subject headings.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were a gift of Dr. Kenneth D. Richert, 1995.
Previous Citation
William E. Guckert Papers, 1930-1977, AIS.1995.05, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Guckert, William E., 1908-1986, Papers, ca. 1930-1970, ais 95:5
Firearms -- Law and legislation -- Pennsylvania; Water -- Pollution -- Pennsylvania; Ecology -- Pennsylvania; Environmental protection -- Pennsylvania; Conservationists -- Pennsylvania; Personal papers; Environment; Pennsylvania Fish Commission; American Wildlife Institute; Guckert, William E.; National Rifle Association of America; Pennsylvania Game Commission; Pennsylvania. Sanitary Water Board
- Allegheny County Sportsman's League, 1932-1950; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I reflects Guckert's time as secretary of the Allegheny County Sportsmen's League(ACSL)from 1932-1950. The papers consist of meeting minutes, financial reports, constitution by-laws, membership, and correspondence.
  - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Membership (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Expenses (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1932-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9-13)
  - Secretary Correspondence, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 14-22)
  - Secretary Correspondence, 1941-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1-16)
  - Reports (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Events (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Outdoor News Bulletin, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Wildlife Federation Bulletin, 1938,1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - East Fork Sportsmen's Association, 1940,1941 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clean Streams, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Conservation News, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Federation News bulletins with resolutions, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Sportsmen Events Memorabilia, 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - ACSL Pins (1943), Metal Car Emblem (1939-1940), Field Day Poster (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Map of State Game Land, Allegheny Co. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fisherman's Guide Map, Emporium, PA; Copy of Pittsburgh Sunday Post, April 6, 1924, on the establishment of the Sportsman's League (Box 2, Folder 28)
- State Land Reclamation Board, 1963-1967; II.
  The records of the State Land Reclamation Board(SLRB) pertain to the actual meetings, actions, and reports of the board between 1963 and 1967. Most of the legislation and research was carried over to the State Bureau of Surface Mine Reclamation in 1967 when Guckert became Director.
  - Legislation News on Mine Reclamation (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mine Drainage Report, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - PA House Bill No.434, Mine Drainage Act, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Guckert with LRB, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Central PA Open Pit Mining Association (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - LRB meetings with PA Department of Mines and Mineral Industries, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - PA Planning Board: Project 70, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Operation Yellowboy: Mine drainage Plan, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - LRB Meeting Minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 10-17)
  - PA Senator Joseph Clark on Mine Drainage, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - LRB Rules and Regulations on Mine Drainage, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - LRB Misc. Strip Mine and Clean Stream Correspondence, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Bituminous Coal Open Pit Operators Manual, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Westinghouse Electric Company Report to PA Department of Mines and Mineral Industries (Box 3, Folder 22)
- State Board of Surface Mine Reclamation, 1967-1977; III.
  A portion of the records from the State Land Reclamation Board, mostly legislation and research, was transferred to the State Bureau of Surface Mine Reclamation in 1967 when Guckert became Director.
  - Appointment of W.E. Guckert as Director of SBSMR, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Guckert Article in The Pittsburgh Press, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - SBSMR Photographs (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Air Pollution (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clean Streams, Water Pollution,and Watertesting (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Allegheny County Soil and Conservation District Annual Report, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - Blair Gap Water Supply Company (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Coal Industry (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Firearms (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - House Bill No.23, Snowmobile Fund, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Republican Party Issues on Mine Drainage (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - State Parks (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Strip Mines of Other States (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Taxidermy (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Senator Joe Clark (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Guckert on Gun Laws (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Reports on Mine Reclamation and Conservation (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Guckert's Speeches on Conservation (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Subsidence Act (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Susquehanna River Basin Compact, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Three Rivers Improvement and Development Corporation (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Statistics on Mine Drainage in Various PA Counties (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Citizen's Committee on Natural Resources (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Received Personal Mail, Originally Called "Fan Mail" (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - Misc. SBSMR Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Agriculture (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny County Sportsman's League (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Allegheny County Conservation District Team and Solid Waste Advisory Committee (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Allegheny National Forest Reservoir Project, with Oversize Map, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Allegheny County Mine Sealing with Photographs (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Andy Anderson, ACSL Event (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Beecher Charmbury Testimonial Dinner, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Clean Streams Law (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
  - PA State Conservation Awards, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Leon Ehrlich (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Farm Field Management (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Firearms (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - PA House Committee on Fisheries Meeting, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Fish in PA (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Tom Foerster (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Kentucky Strip Mine Reclamation Program, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Kinzua Dam (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Maryland Strip Mining Laws, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Mine Drainage and Reservoirs (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Mine Subsidence Legislation (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - National Wildlife Federation Meeting, Pittsburgh, PA, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Ohio Land Reclamation Program (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - PA Department of Health (Box 5, Folder 27-28)
  - PA Department of Health, Mine Drainage (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - PA Department of Health Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
  - Quarries (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Research (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Sanitary Water Board (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Richard Schweiker (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Governor William Scranton's Tour of Mine Drainage Areas (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - PA Senator Correspondence on Senate Bills (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Senate Bill 85, Boatmen's Bill, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 38-39)
  - Governor Raymond P. Shafer (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
  - Milton J. Shapp Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Soil Conservation (Box 5, Folder 43-44)
  - Subcommittee on Conservation and Recreation, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Water Pollution and the Sanitary Water Board (Box 5, Folder 46)
- Research, News Articles, and Oversize Maps, 1967-1977; IV.
  This series of records consist of Guckert's research, news article clippings, and oversize maps of PA counties, from 1967 to 1977. The files are ordered alphabetically by subject headings.
  - Clippings, 1.
    - Clean Streams Publication Clippings, 1964-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
  - Articles, 2.
    - Coal (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Conservation, 1963-1969 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    - PA Uniform Firearms Act, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "Gun Facts" used for Legislation (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - New York State Firearm Laws (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Firearms (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    - Hawks (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Walter J. Hickel of U.S. Department of the Interior (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Roger Latham (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - PA Representative John Laudadio (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - L. R. Lindgren (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Outdoor People (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Politics (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Pollution (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Adam Clayton Powell, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Raymond P. Shafer (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Milton Shapp (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Leonard C. Staisey (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Sport Fishing Institute, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Strip Mines (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - PA Strip Mines (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Strip Mines in Other States (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Subsidence (Box 6, Folder 30-31)
  - Research, 3.
    - Research and Applied Technology Symposium on Mined-Land Reclamation by National Coal Association, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Misc. Mine Reclamation Legislation (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Maps of Pennsylvania Counties, 4.; (oversize)
    - Allegheny Co., Washington Co. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Warren Co., Westmoreland Co., Tioga Co., Clarion Co., Knox, PA (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Centre Co., Clearfield Co., Fulton Co., Jefferson Co., Greene Co. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Butler Co., Clinton Co., Blair Co., Bedford Co., Clearfield Co., Cambria Co., Scrubgrass Creek (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Butler Co., Westmoreland Co., Beaver Co., Fayette Co., Clearfield Co. (Box 7, Folder 7)